Records of the New York Skin and Cancer Hospital (Office of Finance) RG.10.9.1
New York University Archives
Records of the New York Skin and Cancer Hospital (Office of Finance)
1802-1946
New York University Archives
New York Skin and Cancer Hospital
RG.10.9.1
2.75 Linear Feet (5 manuscript boxes)
History of the New York Skin and Cancer Hospital
The 1935 annual report of the New York University Post-Graduate Medical School and Hospital gives a brief historical sketch of the New York Skin and Cancer Hospital: "This institution is the oldest hospital in America to specialize in the treatment of skin diseases and cancer. It was founded in 1882 under the name of the New York Skin and Cancer Hostpital, and operated under the name of the Stuyvesant Square Hospital from 1931 until its affiliation with the Post-Graduate [Medical School] on September 1, 1934 as the New York Skin and Cancer Unit of the Post-Graduate." The New York Skin and Cancer Unit was located on Second Avenue between Nineteenth and Twentieth Streets, one block from the Post-Graduate Medical School and Hospital on Twentieth Street. In 1948 the New York Post-Graduate Medical School and Hospital merged with New York University to become the New York University Post-Graduate Medical School.
Sources: New York Post-Graduate Hospital Annual Report, 1935 RG 32.2
Access Restrictions
Repository permission is required for access. Please contact New York University Archives, (212) 998-2641, university-archives@nyu.edu.
Scope and Content
The records span the years 1802-1948, with the bulk of the mateirals covering the years 1890-1945. The majority of the records are deeds, mortgages, bonds and insurance policies regarding property connected with the New York Skin and Cancer Hospital. Many records concern the transference of individual interests in properties to the hospital.
Records of particular interest include Abstracts of title, tracing the ownership of the site of the hospital to Peter Stuyvesant and the Stuyvesant farm of 1802 (Box 1, Folder 1), as well as a notice to the Directors of the New York Red Cross Hospital concerning the exclusion of alcohol as a medicinal agent (Box 5, Foler 14), and the purchase of radium fo the hospital (Box 5, Folder 16). Also included is the memorandum of agreement between Stuyvesant Sq. Hospital (NY Skin & Cancer) and the Post-Graduate Mecial School and Hospital (Box 5, Folder 18). The estate of Cornelia Storrs is frequently mentioned, as well as her shares in mining companies (Box 4, Folder 4).
The materials are of use to urban historians and provide evidence of the development of health care facilities in New York City.
Arrangement
The Records of the New York Skin and Cancer hospitals are arranged based on the original order of the materials. They were received in large envelopes grouped by location, and each location has been arranged as a separate folder. The records are organized into one series:
Missing Title
I. Financial and Real Estate Documents
Provenance
The New York University Archives recieved the records of the New York Skin and Cancer Hospital in 1993 from Muriel Mantel, Assistant Treasurer of the Office of Finance. These documents make up 2.75 linear ft. out of a total of 40 received from that office.
Related Materials
See Related Material in the New York Post-Graduate Hospital Records, RG 23.2
Deeds.; Mortgages.; Title (Property Rights).; Financial records; Financial statements.; Universities and colleges |z United States |x Real Estate.; Hospitals.; Bonds (negotiable instruments).; Storrs, Cornelia; Stuyvesant Square Hospital; New York University. Postgraduate Medical School; Stuyvesant, Peter Gerard, 1777-1847; New York University -- Real property
- Series I: Financial and Real Estate Documents, 1802-1948
  - Abstract of title, deed and extension agreement regarding 20th Street and 2nd Avenue tracing ownership to Peter Stuyvesant's farm, 1802-1911 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Abstract of title, deed and extension agreement regarding 20th Street and 2nd Avenue tracing ownership to Peter Stuyvesant's farm, 1892-1894 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Abstract of title, deed and extension agreement regarding 20th Street and 2nd Avenue tracing ownership to Peter Stuyvesant's farm, 1802-1911 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Abstract of title, deed and extension agreement regarding 20th Street and 2nd Avenue tracing ownership to Peter Stuyvesant's farm, 1802-1911 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bonds, insurance agreements and mortgage extension agreements, abstract of title regarding 340 2nd Ave. block 925, section 3, involving the Klemann Family, 1847-1904 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bonds, insurance agreements and mortgage extension agreements, abstract of title regarding 340 2nd Ave. block 925, section 3, involving the Klemann Family, 1847-1948 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Title guarantee and trust company policy search, 340 2nd Ave. section 3, block 926, 1848-1911 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Extension agreements and assignments of mortgages, many from Auguste Knepke to New York Post-Graduate Medical School, regarding 303 E. 20th St, 344, 346, 348 and 352 2nd Ave., 1883-1948 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Deeds and leases from various individuals to the New York Post-Graduate Medical School and Hospital, regarding section 3, box 926 (including 302-310, 313, 315, 316, 319, 321 and 325 E. 21st St.), 1889-1945 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Mortgages, bonds and deeds regarding section 3, block 25 at 301 and 303 E. 19th St. and 330 and 332 2nd Ave., 1890-1927 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Deeds, bonds, assignments, insurance policies and register certificates regarding 301-303, 305, 307, 309, 311 E. 19th St., 330-332 2nd Ave. and 485 E. 134th St., 1891-1918 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Photostats of deeds from individuals to New York Post-Graduate Medical School regarding buildings on E. 20th St. and 352 2nd. Ave., 1892-1945 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Bonds, extension agreements, assignments of mortgages regarding 223 E. 17th St.; 220 E. 18th St.; 303, 309-313, 315, 317, 319, 323, 327 E. 20th St. Involving Julia Cruz, Mary Lyons, Bertha Monolya, Edward Cunningham, 1892-1948 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Blue Ridge Mining company coupons, 1902 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Estate of Cornelia Storrs--share certificates for various mining companies, bonds and mortgage extension agreements for 159 108th St. agreement of sale of property and indemnity for city of Newark premises, 1902-1937 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Share certificates belonging to Edward Winslow, Sweetser, Pembrook and Company, 1903 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - New York Red Cross Hospital--notice of exclusion of alcohol as medicinal agent, deed for 100-125th St. and Central Park West, 1903-1908 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Bond, Charles J. Walton to Henry B. Auchincloss regarding 354 2nd Ave., 1904 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Bond, assignments of mortgage, extension agreements, deed, insurance policy and documents concerning American Church Building Fund Commissions regarding 20 Lorimer St. Brooklyn, 1905-1934 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Mortgage extension agreements, surveyors' plans, assignments of mortgage, policy of title insurance, agreements of leases, regarding section 3, block 926 including 302, 304, 306, 308, 316, 326 and 328-334 E. 21st Street., 1907-1948 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Mortgage extension agreements, surveyors' plans, assignments of mortgage, policy of title insurance, agreements of leases, regarding section 3, block 926 including 302, 304, 306, 308, 316, 326 and 328-334 E. 21st Street., 1907-1948 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Deed regarding the bequest of the estate of Charles H. Rhinelander, involving Benjamin Aymar Sands and Herman LeRoy Edgar, 1916-1922 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Assignment of certificates of tax sales regarding City of Newark premises, from J. Edwards Wyckoff, 1925 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Bond, mortgage, assignments of mortgage regarding property in Scarsdale, 1926-1932 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Contract of sale regarding 326 2nd Ave. and 304-308 E. 19th St., 1927 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Mortgage regarding property in Glen Cove, Oyster Bay, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Deed and insurance policy and contract of sale regarding 106th St and 5th Avenue, section 6, block 1612, 1928-1929 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Lease for 2-6 W. 45th St., 1929 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Contract and release between the Society of the Lying-in-hospital and New York Skin and Cancer Hospital regarding 2nd Ave. and 17th St. property, 1929-1932 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Mortgage certificates including 1470 Midland Ave., Yonkers, W. 183rd St., Fort Washington Ave., 340 E. 72nd. St., 1930-1931 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Purchase of radium for Stuyvesant Square Hospital, 1930-1935 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Creation of Charles C. Tyler Fund for New York Skin and Cancer Hospital, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Memorandum of agreement between Stuyvesant Square Hospital and New York Post-Graduate Medical School and Hospital, 1934-1944 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Charitable institution status of New York Skin and Cancer Hospital, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Donation of participation certificates by Mrs. Samuel Adam Clark to Stuyvesant Square Hospital, 1938-1940 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Bonds, mortgages, claims on property held by Frederick J. Frost, including properties in New Rochelle, Bronxville, Hempstead, Manhattan, Flushing and the Bronx, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Lease regarding New York Skin and Cancer Hospital, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Series II: Temporarily Separated Materials (Box 6)
  General
  Materials in this box were pulled for preservation work.